
<tool id="mixomics_plsda" name="PLS-DA" version="0.1">
  <description>PLS-DA and Sparse PLS-DA</description>
   <requirements>
        <requirement type="package" version="6.1.1">r-mixomics</requirement>
	    <requirement type="package" version="1.1_4">r-batch</requirement>
   </requirements>
    
    <stdio>
        <exit_code range="1:" level="fatal" />
    </stdio>
  <command interpreter="Rscript">
    Rscript $__tool_directory__/mixOmics_plsda.r

    $inputX
    $inputY
    $loadingVectorsX
    $latentVariablesX
    $latentVariablesY
    $variableNamesX
    $variableNamesY
    $variableNamesIndiv
    $result
    $ncomp
    $sPLSDA_option.sparse
    #if $sPLSDA_option.sparse
      $sPLSDA_option.keepX.replace(",", " ")
    #end if
  </command>
  <inputs>
    <param name="inputX" type="data" label="Input File (X)" format="tabular"/>
    <param name="inputY" type="data" label="Input File (Y)" format="tabular"/>
    <param name="ncomp" type="integer" label="Number of components" min="0" max="10" value="2"/>
    <conditional name="sPLSDA_option">
      <param name="sparse" type="boolean" label="Sparse PLS-DA"/>
      <when value="true">
        <param name="keepX" type="text" label="How many variables to keep on each dimension for X"
             help="(e.g. 10 10 10) Separate values with a space"/>
      </when>
      <when value="false">
      </when>
    </conditional>
  </inputs>
  
  <outputs>
    <data name="loadingVectorsX" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (loading vectors X)"/>
    <data name="latentVariablesX" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (X latent variables)"/>
    <data name="latentVariablesY" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (Y latent variables)"/>
    <data name="variableNamesX" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (X variable names)"/>
    <data name="variableNamesY" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (Y variable names)"/>
    <data name="variableNamesIndiv" format="csv" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (individual variable names)"/>
    <data name="result" format="data" label="${tool.name} on ${on_string} (R data object)"/>
  </outputs>
  
  <help>

mixOmics R package

===========
Description
===========

This tool performs Partial Least Squares-Discriminant Analysis (PLS-DA) using the mixOmics R package. PLS-DA is a classical PLS regression (with a regression mode) but where the response variable is categorical. i.e. indicates the classes/categories of the samples. PLS-DA has often been used for classification and discrimination problems (i.e. supervised classification), even though PLS was not originally designed for this purpose. The response vector Y is qualitative and is recoded as a dummy block matrix where each of the response categories are coded via an indicator variable. PLS-DA is then run as if Y was a continuous matrix. Note that this might be wrong from a theoretical point of view, however, it has been previously shown that this works well in practice.

Visit the mixOmics_ website for more information about this function.

.. _mixOmics: http://perso.math.univ-toulouse.fr/mixomics/methods/spls-da/

----

Usage
=====

Input File (X)
  a tabular file which provides the data for the principal components analysis. It can contain missing values.

Input File (Y)
  a tabular file which provides the responses (for multi-response models). Missing values (NAs) are allowed.

Number of components
  to include in the model, defaults to 2.
  
Sparse PLS-DA
  perform the Sparse PLS-DA algorithm with feature selection.

  when selected, you will need to specify **how many variables to keep on each dimension**, this is a comma or space separated list of numbered values. The number of elements to put is the same as waht is specified in the **number of components** field.  For example, if *number of components* = 3 then this field can have (10 10 15).

----

Outputs
=======

There are seven output files from this tool:

1. Loading Vectors for X (csv format) - list of estimated loadings for the X variates
2. Latent variates for X (csv format) - list of X variates
3. Latent variates for Y (csv format) - list of Y variates
4. Variable names for X (csv format) - list of names to be used for individuals and variable X
5. Variable names for Y (csv format) - list of names to be used for individuals and variable Y
6. Variable names (csv format) - list of names to be used for individuals and variables
7. R data object (used for plotting)
  </help>
</tool>
